Guide to the Henry Duncan Grant Watercolor Sketchbooks and Scrapbooks
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Henry Duncan Grant watercolor sketchbooks and scrapbooks.
1866-1896
GEN MSS 611
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.67
(19 boxes)
Watercolor sketchbooks created and scrapbooks chiefly compiled by Henry Duncan Grant that document his world travel as an officer in the Royal Navy, 1866-1896 and his family until 1900.
Grant, Henry Duncan, 1834-1896
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the William Reese Company on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection Fund, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Henry Duncan Grant (1834-1896)
Henry Duncan Grant served in the Royal Navy from 1847 until his death. Grant rose through the ranks and served on several ships to become an admiral by 1892.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of watercolor sketchbooks and scrapbooks created and compiled by Henry Duncan Grant while he traveled in Europe, North America, South America, and Asia as an officer in the Royal Navy, 1866-1896, and with his family. Grant travelled extensively throughout his career. The geographic focus of his work seems to follow a few broad patterns. Most of his images made before 1889 depict European scenes, a trip to India in 1871-1873, and Greece and the Near East. His work from 1889 through 1891 includes extensive images of the Americas, including the Canadian and United States West. Much of his work after 1891 concerns England, Egypt, and the Caribbean. Duncan painted seashores, harbors, buildings, cemeteries, landscapes, animals, plants, and copies of other artwork. The scrapbooks contain watercolors as well as family photographs and clippings from The Naval and Military Record and from London newspapers about naval vessels and military topics.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Watercolor Sketchbooks, 1866-1896. II. Scrapbooks, 1871-1900.
Harbors -- Pictorial works; Navies -- Officers; Seashore -- Pictorial works; Africa -- Pictorial works; Asia -- Pictorial works; Canada, Western -- Pictorial works; Europe -- Pictorial works; North America -- Pictorial works; South America -- Pictorial works; West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Botanical illustrations; Scrapbooks; Watercolors (paintings); Grant, Agnes Harriet Elizabeth; Grant, Henry Duncan, 1834-1896; Mulloy, O. F.; Williams, Sybil; England and Wales. Royal Navy -- Officers
- Watercolor Sketchbooks, 1866-1900; Series I; (15 sketchbooks)
  Arrangement
  Arranged by incremental size and chronologically within each size group
  - 3.5 x 5 inch volumes
    - Sketchbook, 1867-1888 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Images of a sugar mill in Barbados and Chinese men smoking opium aboard a steamship of the Peninsular and Oriental Steam Navigation Company.
    - Sketchbook, 1888-1890 (Box 2)
      Images of locations and people in South America, and several images of North American subjects, including a American Indian gravesite near Yale, British Columbia, and the Statue of Liberty.
    - Sketchbook, 1890-1892 (Box 3)
      Images of locations and people in South America, as well as England, Ukrainian Russia, and Egypt
    - Sketchbook, 1892-1895 (Box 4)
      Images of Egypt and England.
  - 5 x 7 inch volumes
    - Sketchbook, 1866-1868 (Box 5)
      Views of British warships and the Nordic region.
    - Sketchbook, 1867-1881 (Box 6)
      Detailed drawings of fish and views of Estonia and the British Isles.
    - Sketchbook, 1881-1883 (Box 7)
      Images of European colonies in southeast Asia, as well as views of France and Spain.
    - Sketchbook, 1883-1886 (Box 8)
      Images of sardine processing and views of England, Spain, France, and Newfoundland.
    - Sketchbook, 1886-1888 (Box 9)
      Images of a picnic and game of lawn tennis in Devon, England, and views of Greece, Turkey, and Syria.
  - 5.5 x 9 inch volumes
    - Sketchbook, 1889-1891 (Box 10)
      Images of Europe, South America, and North America, including a journey on the Canadian Pacific Railway from the Great Lakes to British Columbia and his continuing travel through Oregon, Utah, and Colorado in 1889.
    - Sketchbook, 1891-1893 (Box 11)
      Images of England, the Caribbean Area, and Egypt.
    - Sketchbook, 1893-1896 (Box 12)
      Images of England and the Caribbean region, including views of buildings in Jamaica.
  - 7 by 10 inch volumes
    - Sketchbook, 1884-1889 (Box 13)
      Images of England and harbors of European countries, as well as plants in pots.
    - Sketchbook, 1889-1894 (Box 14)
      Images of Canada and the United States, as well as images of Argentina, Brazil, Egypt, and Turkey
    - Sketchbook, 1894-1896 (Box 15)
      Images of England and the Caribbean region.
- Scrapbooks, 1871-1900; Series II; (4 scrapbooks)
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Scrapbook, "Sketches in India, 1871-1873" (Box 16)
    Scrapbook Grant created while Captain of the HMS Serapis. It chiefly includes images en route from the Red Sea to India and documents Elephanta Island and the railway between Bhore Ghat and Mumbai. The volume also includes an ink drawing of a British social club drawn by O. F. Mulloy.
  - Scrapbook, 1893-1896 (Box 17)
    Images of England, Egypt, and the Caribbean.
  - Scrapbook, 1894-1896 (Box 18)
    Consists mostly of clippings from London newspapers and from The Naval and Military Record discussing naval vessels or military topics. It includes an invitation to an afternoon party with Queen Victoria in July 1896.
  - Scrapbook, 1894-1900 (Box 19)
    Probably compiled by Agnes Harriet Elizabeth Grant (born circa 1835), the wife of Grant. The scrapbook includes paintings and drawings by several amateur artists, pressed plant leaves, and about seventy photographic prints. Images include portraits of the Grant family; views of Mont Saint-Michel in Normandy, France; and several photographs by an acquaintance, Sybil Williams, that show scenes in Scotland, October 1895.